<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: _rails_, | Padawan coder]]></title>
  <link href="http://ei-lene.github.com/blog/categories/-rails-/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://ei-lene.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-04-24T00:51:57-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://ei-lene.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[ei-lene]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Decrypting Thinking Sphinx]]></title>
    <link href="http://ei-lene.github.com/blog/2013/04/17/decrypting-thinking-sphinx/"/>
    <updated>2013-04-17T22:47:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://ei-lene.github.com/blog/2013/04/17/decrypting-thinking-sphinx</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3><em>3 things to be aware of when installing Thinking Sphinx</em></h3>


<p><img src="http://ei-lene.github.com/images/2013_04_17/mystery_of_the_sphinx.png"><br></p>

<p>My key takeaway from installing the Thinking Sphinx gem for a project, is that Thinking Sphinx is extremely finickety.</p>

<p>The steps seem simple enough on the <a href="http://pat.github.io/thinking-sphinx/">Thinking Sphinx documentation website</a>, but many errors and hours later, I can attest that it is full of pitfalls for the unwary, or the plain unlucky.</p>

<p>Our initial steps to install Thinking Sphinx for Rails 3.1 and above - <strong>which threw a bunch of errors </strong>- were to do the following:<br>
1)  brew install sphinx<br>
2)  brew install mysql<br>
3)  added the following to the Gemfile<br>
- gem ‘mysql2’<br>
- gem ‘thinking-sphinx’</p>

<p><strong>Things I learnt from my experience are as follows:</strong></p>

<p><strong><em>1)  You need to have a specific (older) version of MySQL installed (5.5.28)</em></strong></p>

<p>Initially Sphinx threw its toys out of the pram because it couldn’t find the correct version of MySQL because brew had automatically installed the latest version of MySQL (5.6.10)</p>

<p>We downloaded 5.5.30 from <a href="http://dev.mysql.com/downloads/mysql/5.5.html - downloads">dev.mysql.com</a>. Or alternatively, you can follow <a href="https://gist.github.com/gcatlin/1847248">the instructions on this gist</a> to install older versions of mysql using Homebrew. This ushered in the next set of fairly obscure errors.</p>

<p><strong><em>2)  When using Thinking Sphinx with a Postgres database</em></strong> (which we are doing for our project)<strong><em>, install Sphinx with both the mysql and postgres flags</em></strong></p>

<p>The next set of errors from our attempt to debug and install TS, were mostly variants of: <code>‘ERROR: source ‘location_core_0’:  unknown type ‘mysql’ ; skipping’</code>, <code>‘Can't connect to MySQL server [or client or lib]’</code></p>

<p>Although <a href="http://pat.github.io/thinking-sphinx/installing_sphinx/mac.html">the docs</a> say that Sphinx will automatically detect whether you have MySQL of PostgresSQL, that wasn’t the case for us.</p>

<p>And the only combination that worked was <code>brew install sphinx -–mysql -–pgsql</code> (we had tried all the other permutations before this one finally worked, sort of).</p>

<p><strong><em>3)  Follow the gem version to the letter</em></strong></p>

<p>After the installation of sphinx, bundling of gems, and running of <code>rake ts:index</code> and <code>rake ts:start</code>, we ran our search in rails console, which returned a Thinking Sphinx object <code>#&lt;ThinkingSphinx::Search:0x3fc3d2550958&gt;</code>, which resulted in the error
<code>undefined method `next_result' for #&lt;Mysql2::Client:0xac86a54&gt;</code></p>

<p>We eventually found the solution in <a href="https://github.com/pat/thinking-sphinx/issues/446">Thinking Sphinx's github issues</a>. Our mistake had been to assume that Thinking Sphinx would work with the latest releases of mysql and thinking-sphinx gems, which is why we had not included the specific gem version in our Gemfile.</p>

<p>But Thinking Sphinx was pernickety enough to require the exact version '0.3.12b5' of ‘mysql2’ (yes, down to ‘b5’!).</p>

<p style="font-size: 70%; font-weight: normal">
Resources: <br>
<a href="http://pat.github.io/thinking-sphinx/">http://pat.github.io/thinking-sphinx/</a><br>
<a href="https://github.com/pat/thinking-sphinx"> https://github.com/pat/thinking-sphinx</a>
</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
