<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: zero | Padawan coder]]></title>
  <link href="http://ei-lene.github.com/blog/categories/zero/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://ei-lene.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-03-01T22:43:51-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://ei-lene.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[ei-lene]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Thinking of learning to code?]]></title>
    <link href="http://ei-lene.github.com/blog/2013/02/12/thinking-of-learning-to-code/"/>
    <updated>2013-02-12T13:54:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://ei-lene.github.com/blog/2013/02/12/thinking-of-learning-to-code</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3><em>My perspectives – why I’m learning to code at the Flatiron School</em></h3>


<p><img src="http://ei-lene.github.com/images/2013_02_12/thinker.jpg" align="left">
Thinking of learning to code, and wondering if it’s worth the trouble, or if you should go solo or sign up to a course?</p>

<p>I’ve wrestled with these questions before and this post outlines my thought process and why I’m learning to code at the Flatiron School:<br>
<a href="#literacy">global imperative – coding is the new literacy</a><br>
<a href="#empowerment">personal imperative – empowerment rocks, impotence enrages</a><br>
<a href="#exponential">optional – exponential learning</a></p>

<p><a name="literacy">
  1)  Coding is the new literacy
</a></p>

<p>Avi said on the first day of school that coding is the new literacy. That really resonated with me, because it’s true.</p>

<p>In the not too distant past, before the days of universal education, reading and writing were considered optional luxuries. Now, no one even questions the need for literacy.</p>

<p>When personal computers first came out, they were considered novel gadgets for a small slice of society – the geeks and bandwagoners with spare cash. – Why would a regular person need to use a computer?</p>

<p>Now, everyone uses some form of a personal computer, all the time, whether it be a computer, laptop, tablets, or smartphones. For many young children today, iPad are often more familiar than books.</p>

<p>Technology and software already underpin most if today’s operations, and will only become more ubiquitous, not less so. And so, knowing how to code – to interact with software with more control instead of being a powerless end-user – will soon be imperative.</p>

<p>I’m educating myself for the future. Do you want to be left behind?</p>

<p><a name="empowerment">
  2)  Empowerment vs. impotence
</a></p>

<p>Coding is empowering.</p>

<p>The Boy and I had an idea for a potential start-up several years ago, but neither of us code. More than two years, multiple developers / programming language changes and a large chunk of our savings later, the prototype is mostly built, but still not to our envisioned specifications.</p>

<p>We felt impotent, because we had no control of our project - timeline, deliverables, destiny. And that has been a frustrating and enraging experience.</p>

<p>I wanted to regain control of my life and my destiny, and the first step is to learn how to create.</p>

<p>That was what really pushed me to learn code seriously instead of doing it part time, on weekends – I wanted to be empowered, and coding is empowering.</p>

<p><a name="exponential">
  3)  Exponential learning
</a></p>

<p>When I first told my friends that I was hopping on a plane from London to New York to learn how to code, most of my friends were like: “Why do you need to go to New York? Why can’t you learn to code at home? It’s really easy to learn from a book or the web. The best way to do it is just to code, and you can do that at home, and it’s free.”
I see where they are coming from, and I think that’s definitely a possibility. A lot of really great programmers have learned their craft by themselves. It requires a lot of time, commitment, discipline, and probably a certain type of personality.</p>

<p>Personally, I’ve tried that, and I’ve realized that it doesn’t really work for me. I’m just not disciplined enough – often get distracted by surfing the web, or doing errands and chores.</p>

<p>Even if you prefer working through your problems alone, rather than working in teams, going to a school can still be a great option, because it can really supercharge your learning.</p>

<p>Having passionate instructors who  imbue you with enthusiasm, and guide you through programming pitfalls for beginners, and instilling best practices, really make a difference.</p>

<p>Although I’m not a natural ‘group’ person because I learn best by doing, and often like to figure things out on my own – I’ve really enjoyed group learning in my first week at Flatiron School.</p>

<p>Getting different perspectives or solutions to problems from classmates has been enlightening. When I’m stuck on something, instead of spending hours on it, I can ask an instructor or a fellow classmate for help. When I get tired or discouraged, there’s always someone else to buoy me up and debug my code with me. – It’s a very different experience from sitting alone at my desk and banging my head on the wall.</p>

<p>So if you feel like you’re going nowhere fast with learning on your own, try pairing up, or learning in a group, or signing up to a school.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hello world]]></title>
    <link href="http://ei-lene.github.com/blog/2013/02/05/hello-world/"/>
    <updated>2013-02-05T17:59:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://ei-lene.github.com/blog/2013/02/05/hello-world</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Starting from zero.</p>

<p>Avi gave a talk on the History of Code at today, and one of the programmers he quoted was <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Larry_Wall">Larry Wall</a>, who once said, tongue-in-cheek, that:</p>

<blockquote>The three chief virtues of a programmer are: Laziness, Impatience and Hubris.</blockquote>


<p>On that basis, I definitely qualify! ;)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
